Hi, this is Matt Baker. Several years
ago, I made a video about the 10
greatest European dynasties. But you
see, back then, this chart didn't yet
exist. And therefore, I wasn't able to
show you on a single family tree just
how big and dominating the greatest
dynasties really were, which is what I'm
going to do in this video for the top
four. As you probably know, I released
this chart as a limited edition poster
when the channel hit 2 million
subscribers. Of the 1,000 copies we
printed, there's only about 200 left.
So, if you want to buy one, you should
act now. Just head over to
usefulcharts.com or simply click the
link in the description or pinned
comment. Now, if per chance you're
watching this in the future when the
limited edition is no longer available,
take note that we also sell both sides
of the chart on an ongoing basis under
the titles European Royal Family Tree
West and European Royal Family Tree
North/ East.
[music]
Okay. So, first of all, let me point out
that on this chart, everything is
colorcoded by country, not by dynasty or
royal house. So for example, if we look
at the Holy Roman Empire, we can see
that there were several dynasties such
as the Auttonians, the Salons, the House
of Hoen Stafen, the House of Luxembourg,
and of course the Habsburgs. But they
are all shown in yellow to represent
that they all reigned over the same
political entity, the Holy Roman Empire.
Now, the reason why countries often had
a change in dynasty, aka royal house,
boils down to the fact that until
recently, the house a person belonged to
was always based on who his or her
father was, never on who their mother
was. Even in situations where the mother
was of higher rank. So take for example
Queen Oraka of Leyon. She belonged to
the house of Jimenez. But when the
throne passed to her son Alfonso IIIth,
the dynasty switched to the house of
Ephria, as that was the house of
Alfonso's father, Raymond. Okay. So,
what I'm going to do now is zoom out and
switch the color coding so that things
are now colorcoded to show the four
greatest dynasties instead. So, now all
of the members of the House of Cape,
including all of its various junior
branches in both France and in other
countries, are blue. All of the
Havsburggs are red, all of the
Oldenbergs are yellow, and all of the
members of the House of Vetin are green.
By doing this, it immediately becomes
clear why the House of Cape beats out
the House of Habsburg for the top spot.
Most people tend to think of the
Habsburgs first when it comes to
powerful European dynasties, but as you
can see here, the Capescian dynasty is
way bigger. In fact, it still reigns
today in two countries. So, let me now
go through each of the greatest
dynasties, starting with number four,
the house of Vetin, shown in green.
Although this house is over 1,000 years
old, it was only around 330 years ago
that it first rose to the rank of king
when Augustus the Strong and then his
son Augustus III became kings of Poland.
Prior to this, the highest rank held by
the Vetans had been that of Prince
Elector. Anyhow, this branch lost the
crown of Poland after this, but then
went on to hold the title king of Saxony
from 1806 to 1918.
However, it was a different branch of
the Vetin dynasty that ended up becoming
even more important. The one known as
Sax Cobberg and Go. This was the house
that Queen Victorian's husband, Prince
Albert, belonged to. Thus, after
Victoria, the next five monarchs of the
United Kingdom were all members of the
House of Vetin, including Queen
Elizabeth II, even though from 1917,
they chose to use the name Windsor
instead. In addition to this, Prince
Albert's uncle Leopold became the first
ever king of Belgium. And thus, so far,
every king of the Belgians has been a
vetin, even though they since 1917 have
used the name House of Belgium. This
includes the current king of the
Belgians, Phipe. But since he will be
succeeded by a daughter, we do know that
eventually the house of Vetin will cease
to reign in Belgium. But there's more.
Because a cousin of Prince Albert named
Ferdinand, who was a Catholic, married
Queen Maria II of Portugal. And thus,
the final four kings of Portugal were
also all Vetins, even though they
continued to use the name House of
Bonza. And then finally another member
of the family also named Ferdinand
became Zar of Bulgaria. And thus the
three modern Zars of Bulgaria were also
all vetins. So that's not too bad for
what was during medieval times a fairly
minor house. Okay, next up is the house
of Oldenberg which like the house of
Vetin is still reigning today in not one
but two countries, one of which is the
UK. You see, although formally there was
no house change between Queen Elizabeth
II and Charles III, technically there
was. That is, if we go by King Charles's
agnatic, meaning male only, line. You
see, his father, Prince Philip, belonged
to a branch of the House of Oldenberg.
Yet another dynasty that goes back
around 1,000 years, and which in my
opinion is even greater than the House
of Vetin. The first person from this
dynasty to become king was Christian I
of Denmark, Norway and Sweden. You see,
he reigned during the time of the Kalmar
union when all three of the main
Scandinavian countries shared a single
monarch. And interestingly, even after
Sweden broke away, a junior branch
eventually ended up ruling there again
from 1751 to 1818.
But perhaps even more importantly,
someone from that same branch married
the daughter of Peter the Great and thus
their descendants became emperors of
Russia. Generally, these individuals are
considered to be Romanovs. But again,
technically they are not because via the
mail line they were actually Oldenbergs.
In Denmark, Norway, the senior branch of
the House of Oldenberg eventually died
out and was replaced by a junior branch
known as the House of Glutsburg. But
keep in mind, this is not really a
separate house. It's still the Oldenberg
dynasty, just a different branch.
Anyhow, this Glugsburg branch ended up
reigning in four different countries.
First of all, Christian I 10th's younger
brother George was chosen to be king of
Greece. And then in the next generation,
Frederick the 9th's younger brother was
chosen to be king of Norway, which had
just become independent. To this day,
the House of Oldenberg still reigns in
Norway, although it no longer reigns in
Denmark due to Queen Margarita's
abdication in 2024. The current king
there, Frederick the 10th, while still
formerly a member of the house,
technically belongs to the house of
Mesaza, which was the house of his
father. Greece, of course, no longer has
a monarchy, but because a member of
their royal family, Prince Phillip,
married Queen Elizabeth II, the current
monarch of the UK is now an Oldenberg.
So to put it another way, when it comes
to the Y chromosome of King Charles,
Prince William, and Prince George, they
all have the exact same Y chromosome as
the last Zar of Russia, as well as the
current king of Norway because they all
descend patrineally from this Danish
king here. Okay, next up is the House of
Habsburg, which again is around a
thousand years old, but they reached the
rank of king even earlier than the
Oldenbergs in 1273,
which is when Rudolph I previously just
a count, was elected king of Germany.
His son Albert I was also elected king,
as well as his descendant Albert II. But
take note that none of these early
Habsburg kings were ever crowned Holy
Roman Emperor, even though that was the
norm for individuals elected to their
position. The first Habsburg Holy Roman
Emperor was Frederick III. But it was
during the next two generations that the
stage was set for the Habsburgs to
become a truly great dynasty. You see,
the next emperor, Maxmleon I married
Mary, the Duchess of Burgundy, and thus
the Habsburgs obtained the Low
Countries, aka modern-day Belgium and
the Netherlands. But then their son
married Joanna of Castile, and thus the
dynasty ended up inheriting all of Spain
as well, which by that point also
included all of southern Italy. So by
the time we get to Charles V, the
Habsburgs were basically in control of
most of the western part of continental
Europe. But it doesn't stop there.
Through marriage, Charles's brother
Ferdinand inherited both Bohemia and
Hungary, which also included Croatia.
And then Charles's son, Philip II,
inherited Portugal. So yeah, nobody
beats the Habsburgs in terms of total
land area under their domain. But you
see, once the Habsburg dynasty reached
this level of dominance, they didn't
actually last long. Although the
descendants of Maria Teresa continued to
use the name Habsburg, again,
technically they were not actually
members of that dynasty. They were
members of the House of Lauren through
Maria Teresa's husband, Francis I, which
is why I think that the House of Cape
deserves the top spot. First of all,
they are way older than any other
surviving dynasty on this chart, rising
to the rank of king all the way back in
888, a whopping 1,138
years ago. Originally known as the
Reverians after Robert the Strong, they
actually produced two kings of France
before the election of Hugh Cape from
whom the dynasty takes its name. At this
point, they took over from the
Carolinians and stayed on the throne of
France for the next 805 years. But you
see, this dynasty did not just rule in
France. It reigned in many other places
as well, such as Portugal through this
line here. And although things
eventually passed to an illegitimate
line, the father-son succession was
never broken, even when the House of
Banana took over. So basically the male
line of Hukape reigned in Portugal all
the way to Pedro I which means that the
two emperors of Brazil can also be
included in the dynasty. Now going back
to France, the senior line of Capcians
was in fact replaced by a more junior
branch known as the House of Velvois,
but they were still male descendants of
Hugh Cape, as were the members of the
House of Borbin, which ended up
replacing the house of Velwa. Even Louis
Phipe I the very last king of France
from the house of Orland was a male-line
descendant of Hugh Cape. And then of
course there's the fact that the house
of Borbin ended up ruling in Spain after
the Hamsburgs died out there. So every
Spanish monarch from 1700 to today
belongs to the Capesian dynasty. It
doesn't matter that there was a queen
here because she married a male line
member of the family. So the ignatic
line remained unbroken. Also take note
that in 1759 Naples and Sicily became
independent with a junior branch being
put on the throne there. So the House of
Cape reigned in southern Italy as well
up until Italian unification. In fact,
they had actually reigned there earlier
back when Louis the 9th's younger
brother Charles conquered the area in
1266.
His descendants ended up reigning on the
mainland portion of Sicily only known as
Naples until 1442 which is when they
lost the kingdom to Aragon. And
interestingly through this branch of the
family, the Capescians ended up reigning
all the way over in Hungary and Poland
because of this marriage here. And
although they ended up losing both
thrones because Louis the Great had no
sons, they did reign in Poland again,
albeit very briefly, when the future
Henry III of France became the first
elected king of the Poland Lithuanian
Commonwealth. Overall, the House of Cape
reigned in so many places that I wasn't
even able to include them all on the
chart. For example, before taking over
the throne of France, the Borbins
reigned in Nav'or. And for most of the
Latin Empire's 57-year existence, it was
ruled by the House of Kourtney, yet
another branch of the House of Cape. So,
yeah, the Capesians were not just kings,
they were emperors. Now, I mentioned
that the House of Cap still reigns in
two countries today. One is Spain where
Felipe V 6th, a member of the Spanish
Borbin branch, is king. But what is the
other? Well, it's actually the Grand
Duchy of Luxembourg. That's because
Charlotte, the reigning Grand Duchess of
Luxembourg, married a member of the
Borbin Parma branch of the Capians. And
thus, the next three Grand Dukes,
including the current one, are all
Capcians. So, that was a visual look at
the four greatest European dynasties,
three of which continue to reign today.
Like I say, there's still some copies of
this limited edition chart available.
So, if you want one, head over to
usefulcharts.com
right now, or simply click the link that
is about to appear on screen right now.
Thanks for watching.